<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc title="OPERATIONS &amp; AI GUARDRAILS">
  <!-- ============ SHEET 01 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · GUARDRAILS" kicker="CHAPTER 9 — AI GUARDRAILS STRATEGY" footnum="01" title="Chapter 9 – AI Guardrails Strategy">
    <h2>9.1 Overview</h2>
    <p>To ensure the Theta Chat Bot provides accurate, reliable, and business-appropriate responses, a comprehensive set of AI guardrails is implemented. These guardrails define how the chatbot processes user queries, retrieves information, generates responses, and handles situations where sufficient information is unavailable.</p>
    <p>The primary objective is to ensure that every response is based on the approved Theta Technolabs knowledge base while preventing hallucinations, prompt injection attacks, and responses outside the chatbot's intended scope.</p>

    <h2>9.2 Guardrail Workflow</h2>
    <p>The chatbot applies multiple validation steps before returning a response to the user.</p>
    <mermaid-diagram>
flowchart TB
    A([User Question])
    B[Input Validation]
    C[Scope &amp; Security Check]
    D[Knowledge Base Retrieval]
    E[Context &amp; Confidence Check]
    F[AI Response Generation]
    G[Response Validation]
    H([Return Response])

    A --&gt; B
    B --&gt; C
    C --&gt; D
    D --&gt; E
    E --&gt; F
    F --&gt; G
    G --&gt; H

    classDef process fill:#1c5d8c,stroke:#0d2b45,stroke-width:2px,color:#ffffff;
    classDef startend fill:#0d2b45,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:3px,color:#ffffff;

    class A,H startend;
    class B,C,D,E,F,G process;
    </mermaid-diagram>
    <p align="center" style="text-align: center !important; color: #555555 !important;"><b>Figure 9.1: Guardrail Workflow</b></p>

    <h2>9.3 Scope Guardrail</h2>
    <p>The chatbot is designed exclusively to answer questions related to Theta Technolabs. Before processing a query, the system determines whether it falls within the supported business scope.</p>
    <p>Supported topics include: Company information, Services, Technologies, AI solutions, Mobile/web development, Careers, Contact info, Blogs and case studies. Questions unrelated to Theta Technolabs are treated as out-of-scope.</p>
    <callout label="EXAMPLE">
      <b>User:</b> Who won the FIFA World Cup?<br/>
      <b>Bot:</b> I'm designed to answer questions related to Theta Technolabs and its services. For information outside this scope, please refer to an appropriate external source.
    </callout>

    <h2>9.4 Knowledge Base Guardrail</h2>
    <p>Every response generated by the chatbot must be based on information retrieved from the approved Theta Technolabs knowledge base. If no relevant content is available, the chatbot does not attempt to guess the answer.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 02 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · GUARDRAILS" kicker="CHAPTER 9 — AI GUARDRAILS STRATEGY" footnum="02">
    <h2>9.5 Confidence Guardrail</h2>
    <p>After retrieving relevant content from Qdrant, the system evaluates the similarity score to determine whether there is enough confidence to answer the question.</p>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Similarity Score</cell><cell>Action</cell></row>
      <row><cell>≥ 0.80</cell><cell>Generate a confident response using the retrieved context.</cell></row>
      <row><cell>0.60 – 0.79</cell><cell>Generate a response using the available context while limiting unsupported details.</cell></row>
      <row><cell>&lt; 0.60</cell><cell>Treat the query as unsupported and return a fallback response.</cell></row>
    </table>
    <p>This validation reduces the risk of generating incorrect or misleading information. <i>(See Section 4.9 — Response Validation for the corresponding system behavior for each confidence level).</i></p>

    <h2>9.6 Prompt Guardrail</h2>
    <p>The AI model is guided by a predefined system prompt that defines its behavior and limitations, instructing it to answer only using retrieved context and decline out-of-scope queries.</p>
    <callout label="EXAMPLE SYSTEM PROMPT">
      You are the official Theta Technolabs assistant. Answer only using the provided context. Do not invent information. Do not answer unrelated questions. If the requested information is unavailable, politely state that you cannot find it and recommend visiting the official website.
    </callout>

    <h2>9.7 Hallucination Prevention Guardrail</h2>
    <p>The chatbot must never fabricate or assume information that is not available in the approved knowledge base (e.g., pricing, commitments, unlisted services). If unavailable, a standard fallback message is returned.</p>

    <h2>9.8 Website Link Guardrail &amp; Response Formatting</h2>
    <p>Whenever possible, responses include relevant webpage source links for transparency. Structure follows: (1) Direct answer, (2) Concise explanation, (3) Link to relevant webpage (150–250 words).</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 03 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · GUARDRAILS" kicker="CHAPTER 9 — AI GUARDRAILS STRATEGY" footnum="03">
    <h2>9.9 Security Guardrail</h2>
    <p>The chatbot safely handles requests attempting to manipulate behavior or expose system information (e.g., prompt injection, revealing API keys or system instructions).</p>

    <h2>9.10 Unsupported Query Handling</h2>
    <p>Topics unrelated to Theta Technolabs (sports, weather, politics, general coding) are politely declined with a standard scope clarification.</p>

    <h2>9.11 Fallback Strategy</h2>
    <p>The chatbot follows a structured decision process whenever sufficient information is not available.</p>
    <mermaid-diagram>
flowchart TB
    A([User Question])
    B[Search Knowledge Base]
    C{Relevant Context Available?}
    D[Generate Response]
    E{Is Query Related to Theta?}
    F([Suggest Contact or Official Page])
    G([Politely Decline])

    A --&gt; B
    B --&gt; C
    C --|Yes|--&gt; D
    C --|No|--&gt; E
    E --|Yes|--&gt; F
    E --|No|--&gt; G

    classDef process fill:#1c5d8c,stroke:#0d2b45,stroke-width:2px,color:#ffffff;
    classDef startend fill:#0d2b45,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:3px,color:#ffffff;
    classDef decision fill:#fdf6ea,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:2px,color:#b5791c;

    class A,D,F,G startend;
    class B process;
    class C,E decision;
    </mermaid-diagram>
    <p align="center" style="text-align: center !important; color: #555555 !important;"><b>Figure 9.2: Fallback Strategy Decision Process</b></p>

    <h2>9.12 Benefits of the Guardrail Strategy</h2>
    <list>
      <item>Ensures responses are grounded strictly in approved company information.</item>
      <item>Prevents hallucinations and protects against prompt injection attacks.</item>
      <item>Maintains a consistent, professional communication style with verifiable web links.</item>
      <item>Delivers predictable fallback handling for out-of-scope or low-confidence queries.</item>
    </list>
  </sheet>
</doc>