<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc title="TECHNOLOGY STACK">
  <!-- ============ SHEET 01 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="01" title="Chapter 6 – Technology Stack">
    <h2>6.1 Introduction</h2>
    <p>The Theta Chat Bot is a modular AI-powered customer support solution that integrates with the existing Theta Technolabs website without requiring changes to the current Webflow implementation. It follows a service-oriented architecture where the frontend communicates with a FastAPI backend through REST APIs. The backend manages request validation, knowledge retrieval, prompt construction, LLM interaction, and response generation.</p>
    <p>The technology stack was selected based on the following four criteria:</p>
    <callout><b>Cost</b> — Minimize development, deployment, and operational expenses.</callout>
    <callout><b>Control</b> — Maintain ownership of application data and infrastructure.</callout>
    <callout><b>Development Velocity</b> — Enable rapid development, testing, and deployment.</callout>
    <callout><b>Scalability</b> — Support future enhancements such as multilingual capabilities, analytics, and increased user traffic without requiring major architectural changes.</callout>
    <p>The system is organized into four independent layers — Frontend, Backend, AI &amp; Knowledge Retrieval, and Infrastructure — allowing each layer to be maintained, scaled, or replaced independently.</p>
    <p>The architecture is designed to:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Reuse the existing Webflow website</item>
      <item>Keep infrastructure lightweight and cost-effective</item>
      <item>Support future AI provider changes</item>
      <item>Enable modular feature expansion</item>
      <item>Simplify deployment using Docker</item>
    </list>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 02 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="02">
    <h2>6.2 Technology Stack Overview</h2>
    <mermaid-diagram>
flowchart TD
    subgraph Client ["Client Layer"]
        UI["Webflow Chat Widget (JS/CSS)"]
    end
    subgraph App ["Application Layer"]
        N["Nginx Reverse Proxy"]
        API["FastAPI Backend (Python)"]
    end
    subgraph Knowledge ["Knowledge Layer"]
        EMB["Sentence Transformers"]
        DB[("Vector DB (Qdrant/PostgreSQL)")]
    end
    subgraph Intelligence ["AI Layer"]
        LLM["Google Gemini / OpenAI"]
    end

    UI &lt;--&gt;|HTTPS REST API| N
    N &lt;--&gt; API
    API --&gt;|Text Chunk| EMB
    EMB --&gt;|Vector| DB
    API &lt;--&gt;|Prompt context| LLM

    %% Styling
    classDef process fill:#1c5d8c,stroke:#0d2b45,stroke-width:2px,color:#ffffff;
    classDef highlight fill:#fdf6ea,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:2px,color:#b5791c;
    classDef startend fill:#0d2b45,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:3px,color:#ffffff;
    
    class UI highlight;
    class N,API,EMB,DB process;
    class LLM startend;
    </mermaid-diagram>
    <p>The Theta Chat Bot is built on a modern, modular technology stack that emphasizes scalability, maintainability, performance, and cost-effectiveness. Each technology was selected for its suitability for AI application development, ease of integration, community support, and flexibility for future enhancements. This modular architecture allows individual components to be upgraded or replaced with minimal impact on the overall system.</p>
    <p><b>Table 6.1: Technology Stack Overview</b></p>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Layer</cell><cell>Technology</cell><cell>Role</cell><cell>Reason / Consideration</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Chat Interface</cell><cell>Custom JavaScript Widget</cell><cell>Provides the chatbot's user interface and communicates with the backend</cell><cell>Lightweight, framework-agnostic, and easily integrated into the existing Webflow website</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Programming Language</cell><cell>Python</cell><cell>Core backend and AI application development</cell><cell>Easy to learn, broad adoption in AI/ML engineering, and a rich, mature AI/ML library ecosystem</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Backend</cell><cell>FastAPI</cell><cell>Handles REST APIs, request validation, AI orchestration, and business logic</cell><cell>High-performance asynchronous framework with native Python AI ecosystem integration and automatic API documentation</cell></row>
      <row><cell>AI Model</cell><cell>Google Gemini / OpenAI</cell><cell>Generates natural language responses</cell><cell>Modular design allows switching between LLM providers with minimal code changes</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Embedding Model</cell><cell>Sentence Transformers</cell><cell>Generates vector embeddings for semantic search</cell><cell>Runs locally, eliminating API costs while supporting offline deployment and full control over embedding generation</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Vector Store / Database</cell><cell>Qdrant or PostgreSQL + pgvector</cell><cell>Stores vector embeddings and performs semantic search for RAG</cell><cell>Qdrant is optimized for high-performance vector search; PostgreSQL with pgvector suits deployments managing both relational and vector data in a single database</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Knowledge Base</cell><cell>Website Pages + Markdown Documents</cell><cell>Provides company information for retrieval</cell><cell>Easily extendable with additional document sources without modifying the overall architecture</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Containerization</cell><cell>Docker &amp; Docker Compose</cell><cell>Packages and deploys application services</cell><cell>Ensures consistent environments across development, testing, and production</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Reverse Proxy</cell><cell>Nginx</cell><cell>Handles HTTPS, routing, and reverse proxy</cell><cell>Provides secure communication and supports future load balancing</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Version Control</cell><cell>Git</cell><cell>Source code management</cell><cell>Enables version tracking, collaboration, and change management</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Hosting</cell><cell>Linux Server (On-Premise)</cell><cell>Hosts the chatbot infrastructure</cell><cell>Provides secure, controlled, and cost-effective deployment within the organization's infrastructure</cell></row>
    </table>
    <h2>Technology Selection Notes</h2>
    <p>Several components in the proposed architecture offer more than one viable technology option. The final selection for each will be made based on an evaluation of project requirements, performance needs, and operational constraints at the time of implementation.</p>
    <p><b>AI Model Selection:</b> Two LLM options are considered — Google Gemini and OpenAI. Google Gemini is selected as the initial model for development and evaluation. The final decision will depend on response quality, latency, operational cost, and business requirements. If Gemini does not satisfactorily meet these criteria during evaluation, the modular architecture allows migration to OpenAI with minimal code changes.</p>
    <p><b>Vector Storage Choice:</b> Two storage options are considered: Qdrant and PostgreSQL with the pgvector extension.</p>
    <p><b>Qdrant</b> – Recommended when the primary requirement is high-performance semantic search with minimal infrastructure. As a dedicated vector database, it is optimized for fast similarity search and is well suited for chatbot deployments that do not require storing relational application data such as conversation history, analytics, or administrative dashboard information.</p>
    <p><b>PostgreSQL with pgvector</b> – Recommended when the application needs to manage both vector embeddings and structured relational data within a single database. This approach is ideal for deployments that require conversation history, user sessions, feedback, analytics, reporting, or an administrative dashboard, eliminating the need for a separate vector database.</p>
    <p><b>Recommendation:</b> For deployments focused solely on semantic search, Qdrant provides the best performance and simplest architecture. For deployments requiring both semantic search and relational data management, PostgreSQL with pgvector is the preferred choice, as it consolidates all application and vector data into a single database, simplifying infrastructure and maintenance.</p>
    <p><b>Deployment Flexibility:</b> The system is designed for on-premise deployment by default, prioritizing cost control. If on-premise resources prove insufficient, or scalability needs grow, the architecture supports migration to cloud platforms.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 03 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="03">
    <h2>6.3 Technology Selection Rationale</h2>
    <p>Instead of selecting technologies based solely on popularity, each major component was evaluated against multiple alternatives using criteria such as performance, scalability, maintainability, operational cost, ease of deployment, and compatibility with AI-based applications.</p>
    <h2>6.3.1 Backend Framework Selection</h2>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Technology</cell><cell>Advantages</cell><cell>Limitations</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Flask</cell><cell>Lightweight and simple</cell><cell>Limited support for asynchronous APIs</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Django</cell><cell>Feature-rich framework</cell><cell>Overhead for AI microservices</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Node.js (Express)</cell><cell>Good performance</cell><cell>Smaller AI ecosystem than Python</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>FastAPI + Python (Selected)</b></cell><cell>High performance, asynchronous processing, automatic API documentation, rich AI ecosystem</cell><cell>Requires understanding of asynchronous programming</cell></row>
    </table>
    <p>FastAPI and Python were selected because Python is easy to learn and write, has broad adoption across AI/ML engineering, and offers a mature AI/ML library ecosystem. FastAPI provides high-performance asynchronous request handling and automatic OpenAPI documentation, enabling rapid development velocity.</p>

    <h2>6.3.2 Large Language Model Selection</h2>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Provider</cell><cell>Advantages</cell><cell>Limitations</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Google Gemini (Selected Initial)</cell><cell>Cost-effective, large context window, strong performance</cell><cell>Requires quality benchmarking for complex reasoning</cell></row>
      <row><cell>OpenAI (Fallback)</cell><cell>Excellent reasoning and structured output</cell><cell>Higher operational cost</cell></row>
    </table>
    <p>Google Gemini is proposed as the initial LLM due to its balance between performance and operational cost. The architecture remains provider-independent, allowing seamless migration to OpenAI if evaluation indicates improved business value.</p>

    <h2>6.3.3 Vector Storage Selection</h2>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Technology</cell><cell>Advantages</cell><cell>Limitations</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Qdrant (Vector-Only)</cell><cell>High-performance semantic search, lightweight, Docker-friendly</cell><cell>Separate database for relational data</cell></row>
      <row><cell>PostgreSQL + pgvector (Unified)</cell><cell>Unified relational and vector storage, supports analytics &amp; dashboards</cell><cell>Higher infrastructure requirements</cell></row>
    </table>
    <p>Qdrant is selected for deployments requiring high-speed semantic search alone. PostgreSQL with pgvector is selected when user sessions, conversation history, and admin dashboards must be managed in a single database.</p>

    <h2>6.3.4 Deployment Strategy</h2>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Option</cell><cell>Advantages</cell><cell>Limitations</cell></row>
      <row><cell>On-Premise (Selected)</cell><cell>Data privacy, infrastructure control, lower long-term cost</cell><cell>Requires internal server management</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Cloud</cell><cell>Elastic scalability and managed services</cell><cell>Ongoing infrastructure costs</cell></row>
    </table>
    <p>On-premise deployment is selected to maximize data control and privacy, while the modular containerized design supports seamless migration to cloud hosting if scaling demands evolve.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 04 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="04">
    <h2>6.4 Component Interaction</h2>
    <p>The Theta Chat Bot utilizes a modular request-processing pipeline designed for clarity and efficiency. Each component is decoupled, ensuring that business logic, knowledge retrieval, and AI inference remain independent.</p>
    <p><b>Step-by-Step Workflow:</b></p>
    <list>
      <item><b>Request Initiation:</b> The user submits a query through the JavaScript widget on the Webflow site. The request is sent via HTTPS to the Nginx reverse proxy.</item>
      <item><b>Validation:</b> Nginx routes the request to the FastAPI backend, which performs authentication and schema validation.</item>
      <item><b>Vectorization:</b> The backend passes the user query to the local Sentence Transformers model, converting the text into a numerical vector embedding.</item>
      <item><b>Knowledge Retrieval:</b> The system queries the Vector Database (Qdrant or pgvector) to perform a semantic similarity search, identifying the top-k most relevant knowledge segments.</item>
      <item><b>Prompt Construction:</b> The Prompt Builder combines the retrieved segments with the user query and system instructions to create a context-aware prompt.</item>
      <item><b>AI Inference:</b> The backend sends the prompt to the LLM (Gemini or OpenAI), which generates a natural language response based on the provided context.</item>
      <item><b>Response Delivery:</b> The generated answer is sent back through the API to the frontend widget for display to the user.</item>
    </list>
    <mermaid-diagram>
flowchart TD

U([User])

subgraph Frontend
  WF["Webflow Website / JS Widget"]
end

subgraph Backend
  N["Nginx"]
  API["FastAPI Backend"]
  PB["Prompt Builder"]
end

subgraph Knowledge
  EMB["Sentence Transformers"]
  DB[(Qdrant / PostgreSQL + pgvector)]
end

subgraph AI
  LLM["Google Gemini / OpenAI"]
end

U -->|Chat Message| WF
WF -->|HTTPS| N
N --> API
API --> EMB
EMB --> DB
DB -->|Relevant Documents| PB
API -->|User Query| PB
PB -->|Final Prompt| LLM
LLM --> API
API -->|Response| WF
WF --> U

%% Styling
classDef process fill:#1c5d8c,stroke:#0d2b45,stroke-width:2px,color:#ffffff;
classDef highlight fill:#fdf6ea,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:2px,color:#b5791c;
classDef startend fill:#0d2b45,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:3px,color:#ffffff;

class U startend;
class WF,N,API,PB process;
class EMB,DB,LLM highlight;
linkStyle default stroke:#0d2b45,stroke-width:2px;
    </mermaid-diagram>
    <p>This modular design ensures that each layer — frontend, backend, knowledge retrieval, and AI inference — can be maintained, scaled, or replaced independently without impacting the rest of the system. For example, the LLM provider can be switched from Gemini to OpenAI by changing a single configuration value, without touching the frontend or the retrieval pipeline.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 05 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="05">
    <h2>6.5 APIs Used</h2>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>API</cell><cell>Type</cell><cell>Purpose</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Internal — /api/chat</b></cell><cell>REST (FastAPI, own API)</cell><cell>The only endpoint the frontend widget calls; accepts a user message, returns the generated answer + sources</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Gemini API</b></cell><cell>External</cell><cell>Primary LLM — generates the natural-language response from the assembled prompt</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>OpenAI API</b> (optional)</cell><cell>External</cell><cell>Fallback LLM, used case-by-case when a Gemini response fails the quality bar during testing</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Qdrant REST API</b></cell><cell>Internal (self-hosted)</cell><cell>Stores vectors, performs similarity search; called by the backend, never by the frontend</cell></row>
    </table>
    <callout>Sentence Transformers runs <b>locally</b> inside the backend — it is not an external API call, which is precisely its advantage (no per-token cost, works offline).</callout>
    <callout><b>Note:</b> Additional internal APIs (such as session management, authentication, analytics, and admin configuration endpoints) will also be introduced as feature requirements evolve.</callout>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 06 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="06">
    <h2>6.6 Frontend: Integrating with Webflow Using an Embedded Widget</h2>
    <p>The Theta Technolabs website is already built and maintained using Webflow. To preserve the existing website while adding AI chatbot functionality, the chatbot is implemented as a lightweight embedded JavaScript widget. This approach allows the chatbot to integrate seamlessly with the current website without requiring modifications to the existing Webflow structure or design.</p>
    <p>Benefits of this approach:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Integrates with the existing Webflow website without structural changes.</item>
      <item>Simple deployment using a single JavaScript <b>&lt;script&gt;</b> embed.</item>
      <item>Maintains the existing website design and content management workflow.</item>
      <item>Allows independent customization of the chatbot's appearance, including colors, position, and branding.</item>
      <item>Enables future updates to the chatbot without affecting the website implementation.</item>
    </list>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 07 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="07">
    <h2>6.7 Backend: Python + FastAPI</h2>
    <p><b>Python</b> was selected as the core foundation because it is easy to learn and write, features broad industry adoption in AI/ML engineering, and provides a rich, mature ecosystem of libraries (embedding SDKs, vector database clients, LLM SDKs). Using Python maintains a single unified language across the entire backend, avoiding fragmented logic between API and ML layers.</p>
    <p><b>FastAPI</b> sits on top of Python because the chatbot service is fundamentally I/O-bound: call an embedding model, query the vector store, call an LLM, and return a response. FastAPI's high-performance asynchronous request handling allows a single worker to manage many concurrent chat sessions without blocking, while its automatic OpenAPI documentation ensures rapid development velocity and self-documenting APIs.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 08 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="08">
    <h2>6.8 AI Model Layer: Gemini First, Provider-Agnostic by Design</h2>
    <p>The response-generation layer is built behind a thin provider interface, so the LLM is a <b>configuration value, not a hardcoded dependency</b>. If Gemini underperforms on a specific use case later, swapping to OpenAI doesn't touch the retrieval pipeline, the API contract, or the frontend.</p>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Criterion</cell><cell>Gemini</cell><cell>OpenAI</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Cost per token</cell><cell>Lower</cell><cell>Higher</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Context window</cell><cell>Larger</cell><cell>Large</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Reasoning depth</cell><cell>Strong</cell><cell>Excellent</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Structured output reliability</cell><cell>Good</cell><cell>Excellent</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Fit for this project (retrieval-grounded Q&amp;A)</cell><cell>Best default</cell><cell>Strong fallback</cell></row>
    </table>
    <p><b>Testing approach:</b> Gemini is used first for every new feature or prompt. If a response during testing doesn't meet the quality bar (accuracy, tone, or completeness), the same test case is re-run against OpenAI as a comparison pass before deciding whether to switch providers for that use case. This keeps the evaluation evidence-based rather than a blanket provider swap.</p>
    <p><b>LLM Pricing Reference</b> (USD per 1M tokens)</p>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Model</cell><cell>Input</cell><cell>Output</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Gemini 3.1 Flash Lite</cell><cell>$0.25</cell><cell>$1.50</cell></row>
      <row><cell>GPT-5.4 mini</cell><cell>$0.75</cell><cell>$4.50</cell></row>
      <row><cell>GPT-5.6 Luna</cell><cell>$1.00</cell><cell>$6.00</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Gemini 3.5 Flash</cell><cell>$1.50</cell><cell>$9.00</cell></row>
    </table>
    <p>Gemini 3.1 Flash Lite is the cheapest option on both input and output and is the default starting point; GPT-5.4 mini is the nearest OpenAI comparison for the testing fallback described above.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 09 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="09">
    <h2>6.9 Embeddings: Local Semantic Representation</h2>
    <p>The chatbot uses <b>Sentence Transformers</b> to generate vector embeddings for both the knowledge base documents and incoming user queries. The same embedding model is used during both document indexing and query processing, ensuring that all content is represented within the same vector space — a prerequisite for accurate semantic similarity search.</p>
    <callout><b>Key advantage:</b> Sentence Transformers run <b>entirely on the local server</b>. There is no external API call, no per-token cost, and no dependency on a third-party embedding service — making it suitable for offline or air-gapped environments.</callout>
    <p>Why this matters for Theta Chat Bot:</p>
    <list>
      <item><b>Cost control:</b> Embeddings are generated free of charge at query time and at indexing time, with no recurring API fees.</item>
      <item><b>Data privacy:</b> Query content and website knowledge stay within the organization's infrastructure and are never transmitted to an external embedding service.</item>
      <item><b>Consistency:</b> Using the same model for both indexing and querying guarantees that query vectors and document vectors are in the same semantic space, maximizing retrieval accuracy.</item>
      <item><b>Flexibility:</b> The embedding model can be swapped or fine-tuned based on retrieval accuracy benchmarks, model size constraints, or hardware availability — without changing any other part of the pipeline.</item>
    </list>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 10 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="10">
    <h2>6.10 Vector Database: Qdrant, or PostgreSQL + pgvector</h2>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Option</cell><cell>Strength</cell><cell>Weakness</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Qdrant (default)</b></cell><cell>Open-source, metadata filtering, Docker-native, production-ready, no relational-DB overhead</cell><cell>Self-managed; separate database if structured data is also needed</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>PostgreSQL + pgvector</b></cell><cell>Vectors and structured data (chat history, sessions, analytics) live in one database</cell><cell>Higher infrastructure requirement than Qdrant alone</cell></row>
    </table>
    <decision><b>Decision rule:</b> Qdrant if the priority is pure semantic search with nothing else to manage. PostgreSQL + pgvector if the project needs to store chat history, sessions, or analytics alongside vectors.</decision>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 11 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="11">
    <h2>6.11 Containerization: Docker + Docker Compose</h2>
    <p>Every service — the FastAPI backend, the vector store, and Nginx — ships as a container, defined once in a <b>docker-compose.yml</b>, so "works on my machine" stops being a risk. Identical environments across dev, staging, and production; one-command startup (<b>docker compose up</b>); simple rollback by pinning image tags.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 12 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="12">
    <h2>6.12 Hosting: On-Premise Linux, With a Documented Exit Ramp</h2>
    <p>The recommendation is an on-premise Linux server rather than a cloud platform — driven by data control, not cost alone. Company and customer conversation data never leaves internal infrastructure, and there's no recurring cloud compute bill for a workload that's steady rather than spiky.</p>
    <callout><b>Note — hosting is not fixed:</b> if the on-premise server doesn't have enough disk/compute headroom, the hosting model can shift without a redesign. The right path depends on one question: <b>do we need to store what users ask?</b></callout>
    <callout><b>Option A — Don't store user queries.</b> Keep Qdrant as the vector store and add Prometheus + Grafana for monitoring (uptime, latency, request volume). This needs an extra custom container for the monitoring stack and some initial setup work, and still consumes on-premise space for those containers — but no conversation data is retained.</callout>
    <callout><b>Option B — Store user queries</b> (for analytics, QA, or improving answers over time). Move to <b>PostgreSQL + pgvector</b> with Python as the access layer, replacing Qdrant. This sets up a natural next step: a <b>custom admin panel</b> built later on top of the same Postgres instance for reviewing conversations and reporting.</callout>
    <callout>Both options stay on-premise; if space is the real constraint rather than the storage model, either can also move to a cloud-hosted instance without changing anything else in the architecture.</callout>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 13 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="13">
    <h2>6.13 Token Economics &amp; Cost Optimization</h2>
    <p>A critical consideration for any AI system deployed in production is the ongoing operational cost. The Theta Chat Bot architecture is specifically designed to minimize recurring API expenses through strategic technology choices.</p>
    <p><b>Estimated LLM Operational Cost:</b></p>
    <p>Using the default Gemini model, the cost per conversation is extremely low. Assuming an average conversation uses 2,000 input tokens (retrieved context + user query) and generates 300 output tokens, the cost breakdown is:</p>
    <list>
      <item><b>Input Cost:</b> 2,000 tokens @ $0.25 / 1M = $0.0005</item>
      <item><b>Output Cost:</b> 300 tokens @ $1.50 / 1M = $0.00045</item>
      <item><b>Total per Conversation:</b> ~$0.00095</item>
    </list>
    <callout label="ROI IMPACT">At this rate, <b>1,000 complete customer conversations will cost approximately $0.95 in AI API fees.</b></callout>
    
    <p><b>Cost Reduction Strategies Implemented:</b></p>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Strategy</cell><cell>Impact on Cost</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Local Embedding Models</b></cell><cell>100% reduction in embedding API costs. By using Sentence Transformers locally, vectorizing the entire website and all user queries is entirely free.</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Semantic Caching</b></cell><cell>Retrieving answers for frequently asked questions (e.g., "What are your services?") from an in-memory cache bypasses the LLM entirely, reducing API calls for common queries by an estimated 30-40%.</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>On-Premise Vector DB</b></cell><cell>Avoids expensive managed cloud database fees (e.g., Pinecone or Weaviate Cloud) by utilizing self-hosted Qdrant or PostgreSQL.</cell></row>
    </table>
    <p>These architectural decisions ensure that the system's operational expenditure scales linearly and predictably with business growth, preventing unexpected billing spikes.</p>
  </sheet>
</doc>