<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc title="TECHNOLOGY STACK">
  <!-- ============ SHEET 01 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="01" title="Chapter 6 – Technology Stack">
    <h2>6.1 Introduction</h2>
    <p>The Theta Chat Bot is a modular AI-powered customer support solution that integrates with the existing Theta Technolabs website without requiring changes to the current Webflow implementation. It follows a service-oriented architecture where the frontend communicates with a FastAPI backend through REST APIs. The backend manages request validation, knowledge retrieval, prompt construction, LLM interaction, and response generation.</p>
    <p>The technology stack was selected against four criteria:</p>
    <list>
      <item><b>Cost</b> – Minimize development, deployment, and operational expenses.</item>
      <item><b>Control</b> – Maintain ownership of application data and infrastructure.</item>
      <item><b>Development Velocity</b> – Enable rapid development, testing, and deployment.</item>
      <item><b>Scalability</b> – Support future enhancements such as multilingual capabilities, analytics, and increased user traffic without requiring major architectural changes.</item>
    </list>
    <p>The system is organized into four independent layers — Frontend, Backend, AI &amp; Knowledge Retrieval, and Infrastructure — so each layer can be maintained, scaled, or replaced on its own. Concretely, the architecture is designed to reuse the existing Webflow website, keep infrastructure lightweight and cost-effective, support future AI provider changes, enable modular feature expansion, and simplify deployment using Docker.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 02 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="02">
    <h2>6.2 Technology Stack Overview</h2>
    <p>The Theta Chat Bot is built on a modern, modular technology stack that emphasizes scalability, maintainability, performance, and cost-effectiveness. Each technology was chosen for its suitability for AI application development, ease of integration, community support, and flexibility for future enhancements, so individual components can be upgraded or replaced with minimal impact on the rest of the system.</p>

    <p><b>Table 6.1: Technology Stack Overview</b></p>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>Layer</cell><cell>Technology</cell><cell>Role</cell><cell>Reason / Consideration</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Chat Interface</cell><cell>Custom JavaScript Widget</cell><cell>Provides the chatbot's user interface and communicates with the backend</cell><cell>Lightweight, framework-agnostic, and easily integrated into the existing Webflow website</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Programming Language</cell><cell>Python</cell><cell>Core backend and AI application development</cell><cell>Rich AI ecosystem, extensive libraries, and strong community support</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Backend</cell><cell>FastAPI</cell><cell>Handles REST APIs, request validation, AI orchestration, and business logic</cell><cell>High-performance asynchronous framework with native Python integration, well suited for scalable AI applications</cell></row>
      <row><cell>AI Model</cell><cell>Google Gemini / OpenAI</cell><cell>Generates natural language responses</cell><cell>Modular design allows switching between LLM providers with minimal code changes</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Embedding Model</cell><cell>Sentence Transformers</cell><cell>Generates vector embeddings for semantic search</cell><cell>Runs locally, eliminating API costs while supporting offline deployment and full control over embedding generation</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Vector Store / Database</cell><cell>Qdrant or PostgreSQL + pgvector</cell><cell>Stores vector embeddings and performs semantic search for Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)</cell><cell>Qdrant is optimized for high-performance vector search; PostgreSQL with pgvector suits deployments managing both relational and vector data in a single database</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Knowledge Base</cell><cell>Website Pages + Markdown Documents</cell><cell>Provides company information for retrieval</cell><cell>Easily extendable with additional document sources without modifying the overall architecture</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Containerization</cell><cell>Docker &amp; Docker Compose</cell><cell>Packages and deploys application services</cell><cell>Ensures consistent environments across development, testing, and production</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Reverse Proxy</cell><cell>Nginx</cell><cell>Handles HTTPS, routing, and reverse proxy</cell><cell>Provides secure communication and supports future load balancing</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Version Control</cell><cell>Git</cell><cell>Source code management</cell><cell>Enables version tracking, collaboration, and change management</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Hosting</cell><cell>Linux Server (On-Premise)</cell><cell>Hosts the chatbot infrastructure</cell><cell>Provides secure, controlled, and cost-effective deployment within the organization's infrastructure</cell></row>
    </table>
    
    <p>Four components in this table — the LLM, the vector store, and the hosting model — have more than one viable option. Rather than repeat the trade-offs here, each is resolved once, with full reasoning, in Section 6.3.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 03 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="03">
    <h2>6.3 Technology Selection Rationale</h2>
    <p>Each major component was evaluated against realistic alternatives using performance, scalability, maintainability, operational cost, ease of deployment, and compatibility with AI-based applications — rather than picked by popularity. This section is the single source of truth for <i>why</i> each choice was made; later sections (6.4–6.6) describe <i>how</i> the chosen components fit together and are not repeated here.</p>

    <adr title="Architecture Decision — Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)">
      <decision>Adopt RAG instead of relying solely on a Large Language Model.</decision>
      <alternatives>
        <item>Direct LLM responses without retrieval</item>
        <item>Manually maintained FAQ database</item>
        <item>Fine-tuned language model</item>
      </alternatives>
      <rationale>Grounds responses in official website content, eliminates frequent retraining, and stays synchronized with website updates.</rationale>
      <impact pos="higher accuracy, better maintainability, improved trust." neg="adds a retrieval step before generation." />
    </adr>

    <h2>6.3.1 Backend Framework: FastAPI</h2>
    <adr title="Architecture Decision — Backend Framework">
      <decision>Adopt FastAPI for the backend architecture.</decision>
      <alternatives>
        <item>Flask (Synchronous by default)</item>
        <item>Django (Too much overhead)</item>
        <item>Node.js (Thinner AI/ML ecosystem)</item>
        <item>Java / .NET (Slower iteration for AI code)</item>
      </alternatives>
      <rationale>The workload is fundamentally I/O-bound. FastAPI's async request handling supports many concurrent chats, integrates natively with Python's deep AI ecosystem, and auto-generates API docs.</rationale>
      <impact pos="high performance, single language across ML and API, self-documenting." neg="requires team familiarity with async Python programming." />
    </adr>

    <h2>6.3.2 Large Language Model: Google Gemini</h2>
    <adr title="Architecture Decision — Primary LLM Provider">
      <decision>Adopt Google Gemini as the initial primary LLM, but maintain a provider-agnostic layer.</decision>
      <alternatives>
        <item>OpenAI (Used as a fallback for complex reasoning)</item>
        <item>Self-hosted Open Source Models (High operational overhead)</item>
      </alternatives>
      <rationale>Gemini provides an excellent balance of cost, large context window, and reasoning quality for RAG. Keeping the provider as a configuration value avoids vendor lock-in. A data-driven testing approach dictates falling back to OpenAI only if Gemini fails the quality bar for a specific query.</rationale>
      <impact pos="cost-effective, easy to swap providers, data-driven." neg="requires maintaining integration with multiple LLM APIs." />
    </adr>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 04 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="04">
    <h2>6.3.3 Vector Storage: Qdrant, or PostgreSQL + pgvector</h2>
    <p><b>Option 1 — Dedicated Vector Database (Qdrant).</b> When the chatbot only requires semantic search over the knowledge base and does not need conversation logging, analytics, or an administrative dashboard, Qdrant is the recommended solution. Qdrant is purpose-built for vector similarity search and provides excellent retrieval performance with minimal infrastructure overhead.</p>
    <p><b>Option 2 — PostgreSQL with pgvector.</b> When the application requires conversation history, user feedback, operational metrics, API logs, or an administrative dashboard, PostgreSQL with the pgvector extension is the recommended architecture. In this approach, PostgreSQL stores both relational application data and vector embeddings using the pgvector extension within a single database system, eliminating the need for a separate vector database.</p>
    <p>This is the same fork that determines the hosting/monitoring approach in Section 6.3.5 (Option A vs. Option B) — the choice is made once and applies consistently across both.</p>

    <h2>6.3.4 Embeddings: Sentence Transformers (Local)</h2>
    <adr title="Architecture Decision — Local Embeddings">
      <decision>Run Sentence Transformers locally instead of using an external embedding API.</decision>
      <alternatives>
        <item>OpenAI / Gemini Embedding APIs (Recurring per-token costs)</item>
      </alternatives>
      <rationale>Generating embeddings locally eliminates per-token API costs, works entirely offline, keeps data within the organization's infrastructure, and guarantees vectors remain in the same semantic space for both query and document representation.</rationale>
      <impact pos="zero API cost for embeddings, strong data privacy, offline support." neg="consumes local compute resources." />
    </adr>

    <h2>6.3.5 Deployment &amp; Hosting: On-Premise, With a Documented Exit Ramp</h2>
    <adr title="Architecture Decision — Deployment Infrastructure">
      <decision>Host the chatbot infrastructure on an on-premise Linux server by default.</decision>
      <alternatives>
        <item>Managed Cloud Services (Elastic scalability, ongoing recurring costs)</item>
      </alternatives>
      <rationale>An on-premise approach avoids recurring cloud compute bills for a steady, non-spiky workload. Internal server management is treated as a one-time setup cost rather than an ongoing operational expense. If compute needs grow, the hosting model can easily shift to the cloud without redesigning the architecture.</rationale>
      <impact pos="lower long-term cost, maximum data control." neg="requires internal server management and upfront setup." />
    </adr>

    <h2>6.3.6 Containerization: Docker + Docker Compose</h2>
    <p>Every service — the FastAPI backend, the vector store, and Nginx — ships as a container, defined once in a <b>docker-compose.yml</b>, so "works on my machine" stops being a risk. This gives identical environments across dev, staging, and production, a one-command startup (<b>docker compose up</b>), and simple rollback by pinning image tags.</p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 05 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="05">
    <h2>6.4 Component Interaction</h2>
    <p>The Theta Chat Bot follows a modular request-processing workflow in which each component handles one stage of the chatbot lifecycle. User interactions begin through the custom JavaScript chat widget embedded in the existing Webflow website. The widget communicates with the backend through secure REST APIs exposed by the FastAPI application.</p>
    <p><b>Step-by-step request flow:</b></p>
    <list>
      <item><b>Request Initiation:</b> The user submits a query through the JavaScript widget. The request is sent via HTTPS to Nginx.</item>
      <item><b>Validation:</b> Nginx routes the request to the FastAPI backend.</item>
      <item><b>Vectorization:</b> The local Sentence Transformers model converts the text into a vector embedding.</item>
      <item><b>Knowledge Retrieval:</b> The Vector Database performs a semantic similarity search to identify relevant knowledge.</item>
      <item><b>Prompt Construction:</b> The retrieved segments and user query are combined into a context-aware prompt.</item>
      <item><b>AI Inference:</b> The LLM generates a natural language response.</item>
      <item><b>Response Delivery:</b> The generated answer is sent back to the frontend widget.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Separating user interaction, business logic, knowledge retrieval, and AI inference into independent components improves maintainability, simplifies testing, enables future technology replacement, and supports incremental enhancements without major architectural changes.</p>
    
    <mermaid-diagram>
flowchart TB

U([User])

subgraph Frontend
  WF["Webflow Website / JS Widget"]
end

subgraph Backend
  N["Nginx"]
  API["FastAPI Backend"]
  PB["Prompt Builder"]
end

subgraph Knowledge
  EMB["Sentence Transformers"]
  DB[(Qdrant / PostgreSQL + pgvector)]
end

subgraph AI
  LLM["Google Gemini / OpenAI"]
end

U -->|Chat Message| WF
WF -->|HTTPS| N
N --> API
API --> EMB
EMB --> DB
DB -->|Relevant Documents| PB
API -->|User Query| PB
PB -->|Final Prompt| LLM
LLM --> API
API -->|Response| WF
WF --> U

%% Styling
classDef process fill:#1c5d8c,stroke:#0d2b45,stroke-width:2px,color:#ffffff;
classDef highlight fill:#fdf6ea,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:2px,color:#b5791c;
classDef startend fill:#0d2b45,stroke:#e8a33d,stroke-width:3px,color:#ffffff;

class U startend;
class WF,N,API,PB process;
class EMB,DB,LLM highlight;
linkStyle default stroke:#0d2b45,stroke-width:2px;
    </mermaid-diagram>
    <p align="center" style="text-align: center !important; color: #555555 !important;"><b>Figure 6.1: Component Interaction Architecture</b></p>
  </sheet>

  <!-- ============ SHEET 06 ============ -->
  <sheet label="THETA CHATBOT · TECHNOLOGY" kicker="CHAPTER 6 — TECHNOLOGY STACK" footnum="06">
    <h2>6.5 APIs Used</h2>
    <table>
      <row header="1"><cell>API</cell><cell>Type</cell><cell>Purpose</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Internal — /api/chat</b></cell><cell>REST (FastAPI)</cell><cell>The only endpoint the frontend widget calls; accepts a user message, returns the generated answer + sources</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Gemini API</b></cell><cell>External</cell><cell>Primary LLM — generates the natural-language response from the assembled prompt</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>OpenAI API</b> <i>(optional)</i></cell><cell>External</cell><cell>Fallback LLM, used case-by-case when a Gemini response fails the quality bar during testing</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Gemini Embedding API</b></cell><cell>External</cell><cell>Alternative embedding generator to Sentence Transformers, if a hosted embedding service is preferred over running locally</cell></row>
      <row><cell><b>Qdrant REST API</b></cell><cell>Internal (self-hosted)</cell><cell>Stores vectors, performs similarity search; called by the backend, never by the frontend</cell></row>
    </table>
    <callout>This is a basic example of the API surface at the current stage — more internal endpoints (e.g. for feedback, session handling, or an admin dashboard) will be added as the backend grows.</callout>
    
    <h2>6.6 Frontend: Integrating with Webflow Using an Embedded Widget</h2>
    <p>The Theta Technolabs website is already built and maintained on Webflow. To preserve it while adding chatbot functionality, the chatbot is implemented as a lightweight embedded JavaScript widget rather than a rebuild — a single <b>&lt;script&gt;</b> embed, no changes to the existing Webflow structure or design.</p>
    <p>This gets the project:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Integration with the existing Webflow website without structural changes.</item>
      <item>Simple deployment via one <b>&lt;script&gt;</b> tag.</item>
      <item>Preservation of the existing design and content-management workflow.</item>
      <item>Independent customization of the chatbot's appearance — colors, position, branding — separate from the site itself.</item>
      <item>The ability to update the chatbot later without touching the website implementation.</item>
    </list>
  </sheet>
</doc>