<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc title="EXECUTIVE SUMMARY">
  <!-- ============ SHEET 01 ============ -->
  <sheet label="EXECUTIVE SUMMARY" kicker="INTRODUCTION" footnum="01" title="1. Executive Summary">
    <h2>1. Executive Summary</h2>
    <h3>1.1 Introduction The Theta Chat Bot is an AI-powered virtual assistant designed for the Theta Technolabs website. It helps visitors quickly find information about the company, services, technologies, case studies, careers, and other business offerings without manually searching through multiple web pages. Unlike a general-purpose AI chatbot, the Theta Chat Bot works only with approved company information. It does not search the internet or answer unrelated questions. This ensures that users receive accurate, consistent, and trustworthy information based on Theta Technolabs' official content. The chatbot will appear as a floating chat widget in the bottom-right corner of the website, allowing visitors to interact with it from any page.</h3>
    <h3>1.2 Project Goals The primary goals of the chatbot are: Provide instant answers to visitor questions. Help users explore Theta Technolabs' services and solutions. Reduce the time users spend searching the website. Increase engagement by guiding users to relevant pages. Provide accurate information based only on approved company content. Reduce the workload on the sales and support teams by answering common questions.</h3>
    <h3>1.3 Key Features The chatbot will support the following capabilities: Answer questions about the company. Explain services offered by Theta Technolabs. Provide information about technologies and expertise. Answer frequently asked questions (FAQs). Guide users to relevant service or contact pages. Share the official website link for the referenced information. Handle greetings and general navigation assistance. Respond politely when a question is outside the chatbot's knowledge.</h3>
    <h3>1.4 Scope The chatbot is designed specifically for the Theta Technolabs website. It will answer questions related to: Company information AI Development Mobile App Development Web Development IoT Solutions Blockchain Solutions Cloud Services UI/UX Design Case Studies Blogs Careers Contact Information Company Technologies FAQs The chatbot will not provide: Personal opinions Medical advice Legal advice Financial advice Current news Internet search results Information unrelated to Theta Technolabs</h3>
    <h3>1.5 High-Level Solution The chatbot follows a Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) architecture. Instead of memorizing company information, it searches a structured knowledge base to find relevant content. The retrieved information is then provided to the AI model, which generates a natural-language response. This approach keeps responses accurate and makes it easy to update the chatbot by simply updating the knowledge base.</h3>
    <h3>1.5 Why We Chose This Approach We selected this approach because it provides several advantages: Accurate Answers: Responses are based only on verified company information. Easy to Update: New documents can be added without retraining the AI model. Faster Search: The Vector Database quickly finds the most relevant information. Lower Maintenance: Updating the knowledge base is simple and cost-effective. Reduced Hallucinations: Since the AI receives relevant company information before answering, it is less likely to generate incorrect or unrelated responses</h3>
    <h3>1.6 Why This Architecture? This architecture was selected because it offers several practical benefits: The chatbot always answers using official company information. Updating the chatbot only requires updating the knowledge base, not retraining the AI model. Semantic search enables the chatbot to understand questions even when users use different wording. The system can scale easily as more content is added. Running the system on-premise ensures complete control over data and infrastructure.</h3>
    <h3>1.7 Expected User Experience A visitor opens the Theta Technolabs website and notices the chat icon in the bottom-right corner. The visitor asks: "Do you develop AI Agents?" The chatbot searches the knowledge base, retrieves the relevant AI services content, generates a concise answer, and responds with: "Yes. Theta Technolabs develops custom AI agents, conversational AI solutions, LLM applications, and intelligent automation systems tailored to business needs." It then provides: Related Page: https://www.thetatechnolabs.com/artificial-intelligence This allows users to both receive an immediate answer and continue exploring the official website. Excellent. This is Chapter 2: Overall Approach. I've written it in simple, professional language so anyone (developer, QA, manager, intern, or client) can un</h3>
  </sheet>
</doc>